Register of the Will Clayton papers, 1896-1990
Hoover Institution Archives
Will Clayton Papers,
1896-1990
88015
Clayton, Will (William Lockhart), 1880-1966
18 manuscript boxes, 1 envelope (7.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, interview transcripts, speeches and writings, memoranda, notes, printed matter, and photographs, relating to post-World War II American foreign policy, especially formulation of the Marshall Plan, international trade policy, and Atlantic unity; the cotton industry; and family affairs. Includes original family correspondence, especially between Will Clayton and his fiancee Susan Vaughan, 1897-1902; copies of State Department documents and other papers; and papers of Ellen Garwood, daughter and biographer of Will Clayton, relating to her father.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1988.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in Socrates is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
United States--Foreign relations--1945-1989; United States--Foreign relations--1945-1953; Economic assistance, American--Europe; Commerce; United States--Foreign relations--Europe; Europe--Foreign relations--United States; Cotton trade--United States; United States. Dept. of State; United States--Foreign relations; Europe; Reconstruction (1939-1951)--Europe; Statesmen--United States
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
1880 Feb. 7 Born, Tupelo, Mississippi
1902 Aug. 14 Married Susan Vaughan
1904 Co-founder, Anderson, Clayton & Co., Houston, Texas
1918 Member, Committee on Cotton Distribution, War Industries Board
1940-1942 Vice-President, Export-Import Bank
1942-1944 Assistant Secretary of Commerce
1944 Administrator, Surplus War Property Administration
1944-1945 Assistant Secretary of State
1945-1947 Undersecretary of State for Economic Affairs
1947 Head, U.S. Delegation, United Nations Conference on Trade and Employment, Havana, Cuba
1946-1949 Alternate Governor, World Bank
1949-1961 Vice President, Atlantic Union Committee
1950 Author, We Must Trade Sovereignty for Freedom
1951-1954 Member, National Security Training Commission
1955 Author, The Road to Peace
1958 Author, What Price Oil?
1958 Author, We Are Losing the Cold War
1960 Chairman, National Committee on Campaign Contributions and Expenditures
1960- Board of Governors, Atlantic Institute
1961 Co-Chairman, U.S. Citizens Commission on NATO
1966 Feb. 9 Died, Houston, Texas
SERIES DESCRIPTION
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1799-1986. (Box 1)
  Notes, biographical sketches, itineraries, clippings, correspondence, legal documents, and genealogy, certificate, printed material, resolutions, correspondence, printed articles, serial issues, list, speeches newsletter, pamphlets, programs, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by form.
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1925-1986. (Boxes 2-3)
  Typescript and printed copies, serial issues, notes, interviews conducted by Ellen Clayton Garwood, press releases, memoranda, correspondence, and clippings. Arranged chronologically.
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1896-1978. (Boxes 3-15)
  Family and professional correspondence of William L. Clayton, sympathy letters, and correspondence of Mrs. Ellen Clayton Garwood, primarily relating to her biography of her father. Arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  NOTE: Boxes 4-14 (family correspondence) are RESTRICTED.
- ELLEN CLAYTON GARWOOD BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1953-1989. (Boxes 16-17)
  Printed articles, clippings, correspondence, promotional material, and miscellany. Primarily relates to Ellen Clayton Garwood's biography of her father. Arranged alphabetically by form.
- SUBJECT FILE, 1898-1990. (Boxes 17-18)
  Clippings, pamphlets, printed articles, leaflets, programs, speeches, newsletters, notes, serial issues, reports, correspondence, lists, memoranda, bulletins, oral history interviews, position papers, book reviews, and miscellany. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, c. 1899-c. 1960. (10. A-V)
  See photo card catalog for description
CONTAINER LIST
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1799-1986
  - General
    - General. Notes, biographical sketches, itineraries, clippings, and miscellany, 1903-1986 (Box 1., Folder 1)
    - Family background. Correspondence, legal documents, and genealogy, 1799-1984 (Folder 2)
    - Susan Vaughan Clayton (Mrs. William Clayton). Certificate, biographical sketches, printed material, resolution, correspondence, and miscellany, 1937-1978 (Folder 3)
  - Articles. List, speech, clippings, serial issue, and other printed material (includes Will Clayton: Economic Statesman, by William L. Garwood, Jr.), 1937-1978 (Folder 4-5)
  - Awards and honors. Correspondence, speeches (by George C. McGhee), newsletter, pamphlet, and resolutions, 1949-1977 (Folder 6)
  - Testimonials and memorials. Pamphlet, printed material, programs, resolutions, correspondence, and a serial issue, 1928-1983 (Folder 7)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1925-1986
  - General
    - General. Notes, interviews conducted by Ellen Clayton Garwood, partial list of speeches, clippings, and miscellany, 1947-1986 (Box 2., Folder 1-2)
    - Atlantic Union. Clippings, 1949-1950 (Folder 3)
    - Common markets. Typescript and printed copies describing statements by Clayton, 1960-1963 (Folder 4)
    - Cotton. Photocopies of printed articles from the ACCO Press, 1930-1937 (Folder 5)
  - Interview, 1925 Jan. 8. Typescript and letter (Folder 6)
  - Testimony, Senate Committee on Agriculture and Forestry, 1936 April. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - "America's Stake in World Trade," 1943 Oct. 25. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "How Will We Dispose of Surplus War Stocks?" Philadelphia Inquirer, 1944 April 23. Printed copy (Folder 9)
  - Letter to the Editor, Life (unpublished?), 1944 Sept. 16. Relates to surplus government property. Mimeograph copy with related letter (Folder 10)
  - Speech, 1944 April 30. Relates to surplus government property. Typescript (Folder 11)
  - Speech, 1944 Oct. 19. Relates to post-World War II economic development. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "Comment on Dean Hoover's Study of International Trade and Domestic Employment," 1944 Nov. 18. Typescript (Folder 13)
  - Statement, Senate Foreign Relations Committee, 1944 Dec. 12. Relates to confirmation as Assistant Secretary of State. Typescript (Folder 14)
  - Statement at Inter-American Conference on Problems of War and Peace, 1945 Feb. 27. Press release (Folder 15)
  - Speech, 1945 March 17. Relates to post-World War II foreign economic policy. Press release (Folder 16)
  - Speech, 1945 March 24. Relates to post-World War II foreign economic policy. Press release (Folder 17)
  - Testimony, House Ways and Means Committee, 1945 April 20. Relates to reciprocal trade agreements. Printed transcript (Folder 18)
  - "The Foreign Economic Policy of the State Department," 1945 May 21. Press release (Folder 19)
  - "Is UNRRA Doing Its Job?" 1945 Oct. 20. Printed transcript of a radio broadcast (Folder 20)
  - "Proposals for Expansion of World Trade and Employment," 1945 Nov. Typescript excerpt with cover letter to James Byrnes (Folder 21)
  - Testimony, Senate Appropriations Committee, 1945 Nov. 16. Holograph copy of transcript (Folder 22)
  - "Answers to Arguments against the British Loan," c. 1946. Typescript (Folder 23)
  - Speech, 1946 Jan. 21. Relates to a proposed loan to Britain. Typescript (Folder 24)
  - "U.S. Information Service in Yugoslavia," Department of State Bulletin, 1946 Oct. 6. Printed copy (Folder 25)
  - "The Foreign Economic Policy of the United States," Department of State Bulletin, 1946 Nov. 24. Printed copy (Folder 26)
  - "Trade Agreement Negotiations," Department of State Bulletin, 1947 Jan. 26. Printed copy (Folder 27)
  - Memorandum, 1947 March 5. Relates to post-World War II foreign economic policy. Holograph (photocopy) (Folder 28)
  - Interview, 1947 Nov. 22. Relates to proposed international trade organization. Press release (Folder 29)
  - Interview, 1947 Nov. 26. Relates to proposed international trade organization. Press release (Folder 30)
  - Speech at United Nations Conference on Trade and Employment, 1947 Nov. 27. Typescripts and memorandum (Folder 31)
  - Statement, Houston Post, 1949 April. Relates to Atlantic Union. Printed copies (Folder 32)
  - "The Atlantic Pact is a Natural and Necessary Step on the Road to Federal Union," 1949 June. Printed copy (Folder 33)
  - Letter to the Editor, Freedom and Union, 1949 Oct. Printed copy (Folder 34)
  - "The Economic Position of Western Europe Demands Complete Integration either with North America or Communist Russia," c. 1950. Typescript (Folder 35)
  - Speech, 1950 April 25. Relates to a proposed Japan International Christian University. Mimeograph (Folder 36)
  - Speech, 1950 June 2. Relates to the Atlantic Union. Typescript and clipping (Folder 37)
  - Memorandum, 1950 Aug. 25. Relates to Atlantic Union and the Korean War. Typescript with cover letter (Folder 38)
  - Speech, Texas State Legislature, 1951 March 6. Typescript (Box 3., Folder 1)
  - "Destiny of America is Linked Insolubly with West Europe," Wichita Sunday Beacon, 1951 March 18. Printed copy (Folder 2)
  - "The Road to Peace," 1951 April 1. Printed copy (Folder 3)
  - Universal Military Training: Foundation of Enduring National Strength, 1951 Oct. Pamphlet (Folder 4)
  - Testimony, U.S. Congress, 1952 Jan. 15. Relates to National Security Training Corps Act. Mimeograph copy (Folder 5)
  - Reply to Walter Lippmann, 1952 Feb. 26. Relates to U.S. foreign policy. Mimeograph (Folder 6)
  - Letter to the Editor, Houston Post, 1958 Dec. 4. Printed copy (Folder 7)
  - Letter to the Editor, New York Times, 1959 Aug. 2. Printed copy (Folder 8)
  - "Foreign Policy," 1960. Typescript, correspondence, and a typescript copy of a clipping (Folder 9)
  - "Tariffs and Trade," Western Business Review, 1960 Aug. Printed copy (Folder 10)
  - "Uniquely Equipped," c. 1961. Printed copy relating to the Atlantic Council (Folder 11)
  - Memorandum, 1961 Jan. 5. Relates to international trade. Typescript (Folder 12)
  - "A New Look at Foreign Economic Policy," 1961 Oct. 23. Joint statement with Christian Herter to the Joint Economic Committee of Congress. Printed copy with letter (Folder 13)
  - "Atlantic Convention of NATO Nations," 1962 Jan. 10. Mimeograph copy (Folder 14)
  - "U.S. Relations with the Common Market," 1962 Feb. 20. Mimeograph copy (Folder 15)
  - "U.S. Trade and the Common Market," Headline Series, 1962 July-Aug. Printed copy (Folder 16)
  - "The European Common Market," Texas Gulf Coast Historical Association, 1962 Nov. Printed copy (Folder 17)
  - "GATT, the Marshall Plan, and OECD," Political Science Quarterly, 1963 Dec. Printed copy (Folder 18)
  - Statement, Joint Economic Committee, U.S. Congress, 1964 Jan. 16. Mimeograph copy (Folder 19)
  - Excerpts from congressional testimony relating to Atlantic Union, Freedom and Union, 1966 April-June. Printed copies (Folder 20)
  - The Testament of Will Clayton, 1968. Pamphlet (Folder 21)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1896-1978
  - General
    - General
      - Letters by William Clayton and others. Includes material relating to the Garwood biography, 1896-1965 (Box 3., Folder 22)
      - Letters to Susan Vaughan Clayton, 1901-1902 (Folder 23)
      - Letters to Ellen Clayton Garwood. Miscellaneous, 1944-1969. SEE ALSO: GARWOOD BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL FILE/ Correspondence (Folder 24)
      - Letters relating to William Clayton (primarily sympathy), 1966 (Folder 24)
    - Clayton family
      - General, 1898-1972 (Box 4., Folder 1)
      - Clayton, Benjamin (brother), 1931-1971 (Folder 2)
      - Clayton, Martha Fletcher Burdine (mother), 1896-1905 (Folder 3-4)
      - Clayton, Susan Vaughan (wife). Outgoing
        - 1899 Sept.-Dec. (Folder 5-6)
        - 1900 Jan.-Aug. (Box 5., Folder 1-4)
        - 1900 Sept.-1901 Feb. (Box 6., Folder 1-4)
        - 1901 Feb.-Sept. (Box 7., Folder 1-4)
        - 1901 Oct.-1902 Aug. (Box 8., Folder 1-4)
      - Clayton, Susan Vaughan. Incoming
        - Undated (Box 9., Folder 1)
        - 1897-1900 June (Folder 2-5)
        - 1900 July-1901 April (Box 10., Folder 1-5)
        - 1901 May-Dec. (Box 11., Folder 1-4)
        - 1902 Jan.-May (Box 12., Folder 1-3)
        - 1902 June-1922 (Box 13., Folder 1-6)
        - 1923-1940 (Box 14., Folder 1-4)
      - Garwood, Ellen Clayton (daughter), 1918-1966 (Folder 5)
      - McAshan, Susan Clayton, Burdine Clayton Johnson, and Julia Clayton Baker (daughters), 1919-1956 (Folder 6)
  - Alsop, Joseph and Stewart, 1958-1959 (Box 15., Folder 1)
  - Baruch, Bernard, 1955 (Folder 2)
  - Bohlen, Charles, 1958-1968 (Folder 3)
  - Bradley, Omar N., 1966-1967 (Folder 4)
  - Burleson, Omar, 1962 (Folder 5)
  - Bush, George, 1968 (Folder 6)
  - Church, Frank, 1967-1968 (Folder 7)
  - Collado, Emilio G., 1958 (Folder 8)
  - Connally, John, 1966 (Folder 9)
  - Drummond, Roscoe, 1962 (Folder 10)
  - Duke, Angier Biddle, 1962 (Folder 11)
  - Dulles, Allen, 1966 (Folder 12)
  - Eastland, James O., 1978 (Folder 13)
  - Fowler, Henry, 1965 (Folder 14)
  - Fulbright, J. William, 1956-1966 (Folder 15)
  - Harriman, Averell, 1966 (Folder 16)
  - Herter, Christian, 1959-1966 (Folder 17)
  - Hey, W.A. van den, 1947 (Folder 18)
  - Humphrey, Hubert H., 1965 (Folder 19)
  - Irvine, Reed, 1978 (Folder 20)
  - Javits, Jacob, 1965 (Folder 21)
  - Johnson, Lyndon, 1950-1965 (Folder 22)
  - Kefauver, Estes, 1959-1961 (Folder 23)
  - Kennan, George, 1958 (Folder 24)
  - Kennedy, John F., 1962 (Folder 25)
  - Lodge, Henry Cabot, Jr., 1965-1966 (Folder 26)
  - MacArthur, Douglas, 1958 (Folder 27)
  - McGhee, George, 1970 (Folder 28)
  - McCloy, John J., 1966 (Folder 29)
  - Mahon, George, 1962 (Folder 30)
  - Marshall, Katherine (Mrs. George C.), 1958 (Folder 31)
  - Mason, Edward, 1969 (Folder 32)
  - Monnet, Jean, 1959-1962 (Folder 33)
  - Murphy, Robert, 1964-1965 (Folder 34)
  - Nitze, Paul H., 1958 (Folder 35)
  - Norstad, Lauris, 1966 (Folder 36)
  - Poague, W.R., 1962 (Folder 37)
  - Rayburn, Sam, 1955-1961 (Folder 38)
  - Roper, Elmo. Includes typescript and printed articles and letters from Hubert Humphrey and James Reston, 1962-1968 (Folder 39)
  - Rostow, Walt W., 1969 (Folder 40)
  - Rusk, Dean, 1960-1966 (Folder 41)
  - Thomas, Albert, 1964-1965 (Folder 42)
  - Tower, John, 1965-1969 (Folder 43)
  - Truman, Harry S., 1955-1970 (Folder 44)
  - Vandenberg, Arthur, 1948 (Folder 45)
  - Villard, Oswald Garrison, 1947-1948. Includes typescript and printed article (Folder 46)
  - White, William S., 1959-1961 (Folder 47)
  - Yarborough, Ralph W., 1959-1966 (Folder 48)
- ELLEN CLAYTON GARWOOD BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1953-1989
  - General. Promotional material, clippings, printed article, and miscellany, 1959-1972 (Box 16., Folder 1)
  - Correspondence
    - General, 1954-1989 (Folder 2)
    - Garwood biography, Will Clayton: A Short Biography, 1953-1987 (Folder 3)
    - Rice University. Relates to the collection of William Clayton papers and their publication as The Public Papers of William L. Clayton, 1966-1974 (Folder 4)
  - Notes. Background material for Mrs. Garwood's book, c. 1957-1967; SEE ALSO: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/Interviews (Folder 5)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1898-1990
  - General. Clippings, 1961 (Box 16., Folder 6)
  - Atlantic Union (Folder 7)
    - Correspondence. Clarence Streit, Walden Moore, and others, 1949-1977 (Box 17., Folder 1-2)
    - General. Clippings, printed articles (by Max Eastman and others), pamphlets, leaflet, programs, speech, newsletters, notes, serial issues, and miscellany, 1949-1969
  - Committee on the Present Danger. Clippings, speeches, and membership list, 1950-1951 (Folder 3)
  - Cotton. Statement, history of Anderson, Clayton & Co., printed articles, clippings, serial issues, reports, correspondence, notes, and miscellany, 1898-1979 (Folder 4-5)
  - European Recovery Program (Marshall Plan)
    - General. Memoranda and notes by Will Clayton, speeches, serial issue, letters, printed material, and bulletins, 1947-1990 with Dean Acheson, Will Clayton, Emilio Collado, Lewis Douglas, Livingston Merchant, Norman Ness, Paul Nitze, Arthur Stevens, James Stillwell, Leroy Stinebower, and Ivan White, 1962 (Folder 6)
    - Columbia University, Oral History Project. Interviews (Box 18., Folder 1)
  - Russia. Notes by Will Clayton, c. 1922-1923 (Folder 2)
  - Trade
    - General. Letter to the editor by Ellen Clayton Garwood, pamphlets, report, letter, speeches, printed articles, press release, memorandum, and clippings, 1947-1986 (Folder 3)
    - United Nations Conference on Trade and Employment, Havana, Cuba, 1947-1948. Clippings, position papers, a copy of the charter agreement establishing the International Trade Organization, and a printed article ("The Promise of the World Trade Charter," by Clair Wilcox) 1947-1949 (Folder 4)
    - Wilson, Harold. Letter, program and text of three lectures given for the William Clayton lecture series at the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Tufts University, 1971 (Folder 5)
  - World War II. Printed article relating to war surplus, and book reviews, 1944-1960 (Folder 6)
- AUDIOVISUAL FILE, c. 1899-c. 1960.
  - See photo card catalog for description (Oversize 10.A-V)